<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
	<title>Izaac&#39;s Website</title>
	<link>https://izaac.mammadov.co.uk/</link>
	<description>Recent content on Izaac&#39;s Website</description>
	<generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
	<language>en-gb</language>
	<lastBuildDate>Sun, 19 Nov 2023 20:58:04 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="https://izaac.mammadov.co.uk/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	
	
	<item>
		<title>High-Frequency Trading using a Hedging Desk</title>
		<link>https://izaac.mammadov.co.uk/hedging_desk/</link>
		<pubDate>Sun, 19 Nov 2023 20:58:04 +0000</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://izaac.mammadov.co.uk/hedging_desk/</guid>
		<description>&lt;p&gt;Here is an article I&amp;rsquo;ve written on using a Hedging Desk in Algorthmic Trading. The original PDF Version is available &lt;a href=&#34;https://izaac.mammadov.co.uk/hedging_desk.pdf&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, while the (slightly mangled) HTML Version is available below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;utility-functions&#34;&gt;Utility Functions&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;definition&#34;&gt;Definition&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Different people have different ideas about how much variance they are
willing to accept in their future wealth for higher expected returns.
This is known as their subjective risk-aversion. For example, if forced
to choose between two real random variables $X_1$ or $X_2$ to set their
total wealth equal to, different people, even behaving completely
rationally, may choose different variables. More concretely, if $X_1$ is
a constant equal to 100, and $X_2 \sim \mathcal{N}(110, 20^2)$, a more
risk-averse person would prefer $X_1$, while a less risk-averse person
would prefer $X_2$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Risk-aversion seems on the surface very difficult to quantify in a way
that covers all the choices humans may make between any two arbitrary
distributions representing their wealth. Thankfully in their 1947
seminal work, von Neumann and Morgenstern essentially solved this
problem. They proved the von Neumann-Morgenstern utility theorem, which
states that assuming four very weak &amp;ldquo;rationality&amp;rdquo; assumptions, then
every agent (i.e. person, entity or thing making risk-aversion
judgements) has a utility function $U(x)$. Its choices are always based
on maximising $\mathbb{E}(U(X))$ over the different $X$ it can choose
from.[@VON07] In other words, if an agent is behaving rationally and
consistently, then it must have some utility function $U(x)$ and every
choice it makes between different distributions for its wealth must just
be it choosing the distribution $X$ which maximises $\mathbb{E}(U(X))$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can further stipulate that in a choice between two constants, agents
will always choose the larger constant for their wealth. Hence if
$x \geq y$, then $U(x) = \mathbb{E}(U(x)) \geq \mathbb{E}(U(y)) = U(y)$.
In other words, $U$ must be an increasing function. Secondly, we can
stipulate that for the same expected value, agents prefer certainty over
uncertainty, and so they will always prefer their wealth to be a
constant $pa + (1-p)b$, compared to having a probability $p$ of being
$a$ and a probability $1-p$ of being $b$. Thus
$U(pa + (1-p)b) \geq pU(a) + (1-p)U(b)$, which by definition means $U$
must be concave. Assuming $U$ is twice differentiable, we can simplify
these stipulations to just $U&amp;rsquo;(x) \geq 0$ and $U&amp;rsquo;&amp;rsquo;(x) \leq 0$ for all
$x$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;common-utility-functions&#34;&gt;Common utility functions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Someone with no risk-aversion at all will simply always maximise their
expected value regardless of variance. If expected values are equal,
then they will have no preference between lower or higher variance. This
is represented by the utility function $U(x) \equiv x$. Actually, it can
be represented by any utility function of the form $U(x) \equiv Ax + B$
with $A &amp;gt; 0$ &amp;mdash; these are all equivalent. In general, utility functions
do not change behaviour under addition by a constant and multiplication
by a positive constant, since
$\mathbb{E}(AU(X) + B) = A\mathbb{E}(U(X)) + B$; maximising
$\mathbb{E}(AU(X) + B))$ is the same as maximising $\mathbb{E}(U(X))$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The concavity of the utility function at any point represents in some
sense how risk-averse someone is at that level of wealth, and in the
case of $U(x) \equiv x$, indeed $U&amp;rsquo;&amp;rsquo;(x) \equiv 0$. The Arrrow-Pratt
absolute risk-aversion coefficient, meant to encapsulate this idea of
risk-aversion at a certain point, is defined as
$$A_{\text{abs}}(x) := \frac{-U&amp;rsquo;&amp;rsquo;(x)}{U&amp;rsquo;(x)}.$$ [@ARR65][@PRA64]. Note
that the Arrow-Pratt absolute risk-aversion coefficient is invariant
under addition by a constant and multiplication by a positive constant.
There is also the Arrow-Pratt relative risk-aversion coefficient defined
as: $$A_{\text{rel}}(x) := \frac{-xU&amp;rsquo;&amp;rsquo;(x)}{U&amp;rsquo;(x)},$$ which also has the
feature that it is invariant under multiplicaton and addition of the
utility function by a constant, but now is also dimensionless to the
units of $x$ (it doesn&amp;rsquo;t make a difference if wealth is measured in
Dollars, Pounds or Euros).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we assume that a utility function has constant absolute risk-aversion
(CARA), then we are forced to have utility functions of the form
$U(x) \equiv -\mathrm{e}^{-cx}$ up to equivalence for some $c &amp;gt; 0$.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
If we assume that a utility function has constant relative risk-aversion
(CRRA), then we are forced to have utility functions of the form
$U(x) \equiv \pm x^C$ for some $C \leq 1$,&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; or $U(x) \equiv \log(x)$
up to equivalence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;application-to-high-frequency-trading&#34;&gt;Application to High-Frequency Trading&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A high-frequency trading firm will have some concept of wealth (which
can be defined to be its total net assets) and will be making
expected-value/variance trade-offs every second. Von Neumann-Morgenstern
states that (if it is being run rationally and consistently), it must be
maximising some expected utility on its total net assets. A common
misconception is that trading firms have no risk-aversion and are only
trying to maximise expected value ($U(x) \equiv x$), however that would
mean that the company should take infinitely sized positive
expected-value bets and never hedge. Unfortunately, without an infinite
balance sheet, this can only end badly.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What that utility function specifically should be can be a decision left
to the stakeholders of the company and all of the discussion below is
applicable to all choices of utility function. However, out of all the
commonly used utility functions, one stands out as being particularly
ubiquitous. That is the CRRA function $U(x) \equiv \log(x)$. It is the
only CARA/CRRA function with the properties of:
$$\lim_{x \to 0} U(x) = -\infty\text{, and } \lim_{x \to \infty} U(x) = \infty.$$
This means that a net assets of 0 should be treated as infinitely bad
(indeed, typically meaning the company has very little future left), and
that the utility is unbounded in the positive direction, meaning there
is always significantly more expected utility to be gained.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, utility functions were originally conceptualised to help think
about trades taken over a fixed time period with risky assets being
marked to market at the end of the time period. This is clearly not a
good assumption in high-frequency trading, where trades are taken at any
time, whenever desired. Thus more care needs to be taken in how utility
functions are used which will be decsribed later on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;hedging-desk-behaviour&#34;&gt;Hedging Desk Behaviour&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;definition-1&#34;&gt;Definition&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We describe a high-frequency trading set-up as follows. There is a
central internal hedging desk which, for every risky asset traded and
for all volumes, quotes an internal bid/ask. Every single high-frequency
making/taking strategy must immediately (market) trade against the
internal hedging desk whenever it receives a net exposure to any risky
asset. A trade&amp;rsquo;s profit can be precisely defined by the net cash flow in
executing a trade including fees and immediately market trading any
exposures against the internal hedging desk. As can be expected, the
goal of a making/taking strategy is to maximise the sum of profits
across all the trades it executes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The internal hedging desk, on the other hand, doesn&amp;rsquo;t try to maximise
its own profits. Instead, its purpose is to provide as tight as spreads
as possible to all of the making/taking strategies while ensuring that
it charges enough spread to compensate for the variance in price of the
risky assets that it holds. The internal hedging desk doesn&amp;rsquo;t actually
execute any external trades but merely quotes internal prices in such a
way as to encourage making/taking strategies to make offsetting trades
where appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;uncertainty-from-the-strategys-perspective&#34;&gt;Uncertainty from the strategy&amp;rsquo;s perspective&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The making/taking strategy faces risk with any trade it executes that
the internal hedging desk price may change in the time it takes to
receive notice from the exchange of the trade going through and passing
on the exposure to the heding desk. For a maker trade, this would be the
time between the last point a limit order could&amp;rsquo;ve been cancelled for a
trade not to go through, and the time the hedging desk receives the
trade. For a taker trade, this would simply be the time between sending
the order and the time the hedging desk receives the trade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the sake of simplicity, let us consider a risky asset &lt;code&gt;XYZ&lt;/code&gt;, whose
mid-price follows a geometric Brownian Motion, and so, its mid-price
$M(t)$ is given by the equation
$$M(t) = M_0 \exp\left(\left(\mu - \frac{\sigma^2}{2}\right)t + \sigma B_t\right),$$
where $B_t$ is a Brownian Motion. We can further assume that we are
working in a risk-neutral probability space and so $\mu=0$, giving us
$$M(t) = M_0 \exp\left(-\frac{\sigma^2t}{2} + \sigma B_t\right).$$ Then,
if we say that our internal hedging desk bid for a volume $V$ of &lt;code&gt;XYZ&lt;/code&gt;
at time $t$ is $B(V, t)$. We decompose this bid as follows:
$$B(V, t) = M(t)\mathrm{e}^{-C(V,t)},$$ where $C(V, t)$ is the credits
of the hedging desk bid for volume $V$ and time $t$. If a taker strategy
sends a fill or kill buy for &lt;code&gt;XYZ&lt;/code&gt; at time $t$ for a volume $V$, price
$\pi$, and then the hedging desk receives a confirmation of the trade at
time $t&amp;rsquo;$, the strategy&amp;rsquo;s profit $P$ can be written as follows:
$$\begin{aligned}
P &amp;amp;= V \times (B(V, t&amp;rsquo;) - \pi) \\
&amp;amp;= V \times \left(M(t&amp;rsquo;)\mathrm{e}^{-C(V,t&amp;rsquo;)} - \pi\right) \\
&amp;amp;= V \times \left(M(t&amp;rsquo;)\mathrm{e}^{-C(V,t&amp;rsquo;)} - M(t)\mathrm{e}^{-C(V,t)} + M(t)\mathrm{e}^{-C(V,t)} - \pi\right) \\
&amp;amp;= V \times \left(M(t&amp;rsquo;)\mathrm{e}^{-C(V,t&amp;rsquo;)} - M(t)\mathrm{e}^{-C(V,t)}\right) + P_0,
\end{aligned}$$ where $P_0$ is the profit that the strategy
sees/predicts at the time $t$ (when the taker trade is sent). For the
sake of simplicity, we assume that $C(V, t&amp;rsquo;) = C(V, t)$, which is a fair
assumption if the internal hedging desk doesn&amp;rsquo;t suddenly have
significant changes in &lt;code&gt;XYZ&lt;/code&gt; exposure or predictions around market
volatility in the timeframe between $t$ and $t&amp;rsquo;$. A more detailed
analysis can be done by considering changes in $C(V, t)$ over this short
timeframe. Using this assumption, the profit $P$ becomes
$$\begin{aligned}
P &amp;amp;= V\mathrm{e}^{-C(V,t)}(M(t&amp;rsquo;) - M(t)) + P_0 \\
&amp;amp;= V\mathrm{e}^{-C(V,t)}M(t)\left(\exp\left(-\frac{\sigma^2(t&amp;rsquo;-t)}{2} + \sigma (B_{t&amp;rsquo;}-B_t)\right) - 1\right) + P_0 \\
&amp;amp;= VB(V, t)\left(\exp\left(-\frac{\sigma^2(t&amp;rsquo;-t)}{2} + \sigma\sqrt{t&amp;rsquo;-t}Z\right) - 1\right) + P_0,
\end{aligned}$$ where $Z$ is a standard normal distribution. Thus:
$$
\frac{P-P_0}{VB(V,t)} + 1 \sim \text{Log-Normal}\left(-\frac{\sigma^2(t&amp;rsquo;-t)}{2}, \sigma^2(t&amp;rsquo;-t)\right).$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This precisely defines the distribution of profits expected based on the
size of the trade $V$, the initial seen hedging desk bid $B(V, t)$, the
volatility of the underlying asset $\sigma$ and the time taken from
sending the trade to the hedging desk receiving confirmation $t&amp;rsquo;-t$. We
can thus calculate that the following statistics for $P$ at time $t$:
$$\begin{aligned}
\mathbb{E}(P) &amp;amp;= P_0, \\
\text{Var}(P) &amp;amp;= V^2B(V,t)^2\left(\mathrm{e}^{\sigma^2(t&amp;rsquo;-t)} - 1\right).
\end{aligned}$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We use this information to figure out if a given trade is worth doing or
not based on a specified utility function and current net-assets. Say
that a trading firm&amp;rsquo;s current net-assets is given by $X_0$. Then the
trade is worth doing, if at time $t$,
$\mathbb{E}(U(X_0 + P)) \geq \mathbb{E}(U(X_0))$. For a log utility
function, that corresponds to: $$\begin{aligned}
\mathbb{E}(\log(X_0 + P)) &amp;amp;\geq \log(X_0) \\
\log(X_0) + \mathbb{E}\left(\log\left(1 + \frac{P}{X_0}\right)\right) &amp;amp;\geq \log(X_0) \\
\mathbb{E}\left(\log\left(1 + \frac{P}{X_0}\right)\right) &amp;amp;\geq 0. \\
\end{aligned}$$ This can be calculated via numerical integration for the
$P$ as specified in the Equation above, to yield a result of whether a trade is worth doing
based on $X_0$, $\sigma$, $t&amp;rsquo;-t$, $P_0$, $VB(V, t)$. In general, we can
see that as $X_0$ grows, we are more willing to do riskier trades so
long as the expected value is positive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that in this subsection, we have made some key assumptions. These
include, the mid-price being a geometric Brownian Motion with no drift;
constant hedging desk credits between $t$ and $t$; only considering Fill
or Kill orders; knowing $t&amp;rsquo; - t$ before the trade takes place; and most
incorrectly, the lack of any adverse selection. We will work on dropping
or improving these assumptions later on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;uncertainty-from-the-hedging-desks-perspective&#34;&gt;Uncertainty from the hedging desk&amp;rsquo;s perspective&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A hedging desk faces uncertainty from having exposure to risky assets.
The hedging desk only locks in profit after buying a risky asset and
then selling the risky asset or vice versa. In the time between those
trades, it faces exposure to the risky asset. The longer the time is
between the position-increasing trade, and the position-decreasing
trade, the greater the risk it faces. We consider the hedging desk to be
a first-in, first-out (FIFO) queue, where each position-decreasing trade
hedges against the oldest position-increasing trade still in the queue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let us say that our hedging desk currently has a position in &lt;code&gt;XYZ&lt;/code&gt; of
$+A$ (long) and trades the asset &lt;code&gt;XYZ&lt;/code&gt; at a rate $2r$.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; If we assume
a symmetrical flow of buys and sells, then hedging trades of &lt;code&gt;XYZ&lt;/code&gt; take
place at a rate of $r$. If the hedging desks further buys an extra $V$
amount of &lt;code&gt;XYZ&lt;/code&gt;, then that new trade will take an average time of
approximately $\frac{2A+V}{2r}$ to hedge. That is calculated from the
fact that it must hedge all of its initial $+A$ position (the hedging
desk is a FIFO queue) which takes time $\frac{A}{r}$, and then it begins
hedging the $V$ amount of &lt;code&gt;XYZ&lt;/code&gt; which completes after $\frac{V}{r}$.
Note that the average time to hedge the trade isn&amp;rsquo;t the same as the time
taken to hedge the entire amount $V$, but rather the time taken to hedge
half of the amount $V$. Because it is a FIFO queue, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t matter if
more buy trades take place before hedging has finished, since those
trades will just go behind this one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We work out how much credit to charge for hedging this trade $V$ based
on the distribution of $M(t+\frac{2A+V}{2r})$ given by:
$$M\left(t+\frac{2A+V}{2r}\right) = M(t)\exp\left(-\frac{\sigma^2(2A+V)}{4r} + \sigma\sqrt{\frac{2A+V}{2r}}Z\right),$$
where $Z$ is a standard normal variable. We define the profit from the
trade to be as follows: $$\begin{aligned}
P &amp;amp;= V\left(M\left(t + \frac{2A+V}{2r}\right) - \exp(-C(V, t))M(t)\right) \\
P &amp;amp;= VM(t)\left(\exp\left(-\frac{\sigma^2(2A+V)}{4r} + \sigma\sqrt{\frac{2A+V}{2r}}Z\right) - \exp(-C(V, t))\right),
\end{aligned}$$ from which we can calculate the following statistics for
the profit of a hedging desk trade: $$\begin{aligned}
\mathbb{E}(P) &amp;amp;= VM(t)(1 - \exp(-C(V, t))) \\
\text{Var}(P) &amp;amp;= V^2M(t)^2\left(\exp\left(\frac{\sigma^2(2A+V)}{2r}\right) - 1\right).
\end{aligned}$$ As expected, the expected profit increases with larger
credits, and the variance in profit increases with larger initial
position $A$ and volume of trade $V$, while the variance decreases with
larger hedge rate $r$. As before, we can see whether such a trade is
worth doing based on our utility function framework if
$\mathbb{E}(U(X_0 + P)) \geq \mathbb{E}(U(X_0))$, which for a log
utility function corresponds to: $$\begin{aligned}
\mathbb{E}(\log(X_0 + P)) &amp;amp;\geq \log(X_0) \\
\mathbb{E}\left(\log\left(1 + \frac{P}{X_0}\right)\right) &amp;amp;\geq 0,
\end{aligned}$$ which can once again be calculated via numerical
integration. However, in the case of a hedging desk, our goal is to
quote prices as tight as possible without losing expected utility, in
order to best facilitate the strategies&amp;rsquo; trading. Thus, in this case,
$C(V, t)$ should be chosen to force equality in Equation above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this subsection so far, we have only described the statistics around
a position-increasing trade, however, what should we make of a trade
that reduces our risk? Once again, let us assume that our current
position is $+A$ (long) and we make a trade this time to sell $V$
($V \leq A$) units of &lt;code&gt;XYZ&lt;/code&gt; at a price of $M(t)\mathrm{e}^{C(V, t)}$.
The credits $C(V, t)$ should be chosen so that our expected utility is
equal before and after the trade. This leads to the equation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$\begin{aligned}
\mathbb{E}\left(\log\left(X_0 + AM\left(t + \frac{A}{2r}\right)\right)\right) &amp;amp;= \mathbb{E}\left(\log\left(X_0 + VM(t)\mathrm{e}^C +  (A-V)M\left(t + \frac{A-V}{2r}\right)\right)\right) \\
\mathbb{E}\left(\log\left(1 + \frac{A}{X_0}M\left(t + \frac{A}{2r}\right)\right)\right) &amp;amp;= \mathbb{E}\left(\log\left(1 + \frac{V\mathrm{e}^C}{X_0}M(t) + \frac{A-V}{X_0}M\left(t + \frac{A-V}{2r}\right)\right)\right),
\end{aligned}$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where $X_0$ is the net assets not including &lt;code&gt;XYZ&lt;/code&gt;, and
$$M(t + \Delta t) = M(t)\exp\left(-\frac{\sigma^2\Delta t}{2} + \sigma\Delta tZ\right),$$
with $Z$ once again a standard normal random variable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that our expected utility logic naturally discounts the value of
risky assets held by the hedging desk. This creates natural &amp;ldquo;skewing&amp;rdquo;
behaviour whereby if the hedging desk is significantly long a risky
assset, its bids will have large credits, while its offers will have
small or negative credit. And since strategies make trades based on the
prices quoted by the hedging desk, this will lead to strategies
naturally skewing their bids and offers based on the heding desk&amp;rsquo;s
exposure. No extraneous skewing logic needs to be implemented if your
trading is based on proper risk-discounted valuations for risky-assets,
as we have described above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once again, we need to point out important assumptions in the model
described in this subsection. These are the fact that the mid-price is a
geometric Brownian Motion with no drift; hedging takes place at a
constant rate $r$; treating the entire trade volume as being hedged at
its &amp;ldquo;median&amp;rdquo; hedge time; and once again, most incorrectly, no adverse
selection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;implementing-expected-utility&#34;&gt;Implementing Expected Utility&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;taylor-approximations&#34;&gt;Taylor Approximations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Above, we&amp;rsquo;ve made passing references to using numerical integration to
work out values for expected utilities. While that is the only way (for
most utility functions) to come to a highly accurate result, in a
high-frequency trading scenario, a much quicker although imprecise
method is necessary. The solution to this is to use Taylor&amp;rsquo;s Theorem to
approximate our utility functions as small order polynomials. The
smaller the size of the trade in question, the more accurate these
approximations will be, and the fewer terms you&amp;rsquo;ll need to still get an
accurate result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Specifically focusing on a log utlity function, we often see an
expression of the form
$$\mathbb{E}(\log(X_0 + Y)) = \log(X_0) + \mathbb{E}\left(\log\left(1 + \frac{Y}{X_0}\right)\right),$$
where $Y$ is some random variable involving a trade and $X_0$ is a
constant representing our net assets. The second term on the right hand
side of the Equation above can be Taylor expanded as follows:
$$\begin{aligned}
\mathbb{E}\left(\log\left(1 + \frac{Y}{X_0}\right)\right) &amp;amp;\approx \frac{1}{X_0}\mathbb{E}(Y) + \mathcal{O}\left(\frac{Y^2}{X_0^2}\right) \\
&amp;amp;\approx \frac{1}{X_0}\mathbb{E}(Y) - \frac{1}{2X_0^2}\mathbb{E}\left(Y^2\right) + \mathcal{O}\left(\frac{Y^3}{X_0^3}\right) \\
&amp;amp;= \sum_{i=1}^{\infty}\frac{(-1)^{i+1}}{iX_0^i} \mathbb{E}\left(Y^i\right),
\end{aligned}$$ with convergence if $|Y| &amp;lt; |X_0|$ almost surely.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first-order approximation in the Equation above involves only
considering the expected value of $Y$. In general, this is the
justifcation for why many trading-firms see themselves as solely
in the business of maximising expected value
&amp;mdash; that is what they are doing, though only to a first order
approximation. Another way to think about this, is that if you zoom in
close enough to any (differentiable) utility function at any point, it
will just look like a straight line &amp;mdash; no risk-aversion and solely
maximising expected value. The second-order approximation in the Equation
above has the same expected-value term, but now
subtracts that by a variance term. Indeed, the larger the variance is
relative to $X_0$, the greater this risk-discounting effect is. In
general, each term in the Taylor expansion just involve higher and
higher moments of $Y$, which are usually analytically known.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;defining-net-assets&#34;&gt;Defining &amp;ldquo;net assets&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout, we&amp;rsquo;ve made reference to this value $X_0$ and defined it as
the net assets of the trading firm at any point in time. In our context,
that is actually an ambiguous definition, since at any point in time, a
company may have exposures to a wide variety of risky assets. The entire
basis of our system involves not marking risky assets to market, but
rather to mark them to their &amp;ldquo;expected utility&amp;rdquo; at the predicted time
that they get hedged. The net assets value should represent the expected
utility of assets if they are diligently passively liquidated, with no
time-pressure, which certainly isn&amp;rsquo;t mark-to-market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on this rationale, we propose the following definition for $X_0$:
$$X_0 := \exp\left(\mathbb{E}\left(\log\left(\sum_{a \in R} A_a M_a\left(t_a\right)\right)\right)\right),$$
where $R$ is the set of all assets, $A_a$ is the exposure to asset $a$,
$t_a$ is the expected hedge time for the current position in $a$, and
$M_a(\tau)$ is the mid-price of asset $a$ at time $\tau$. Using the
assumptions about hedging rates as in Subsection &amp;ldquo;Hedging Desk Uncertainty&amp;rdquo;
, we see this can be written as:
$$X_0(t) = \exp\left(\mathbb{E}\left(\log\left(\sum_{a \in R} A_a M_a\left(t + \frac{A_a}{2r_a}\right)\right)\right)\right),$$
where $r_a$ is the hedging rate of asset $a$. Further applying the
drift-free Brownian Motion assumption, this turns the equations into:
$$X_0(t) = \exp\left(\mathbb{E}\left(\log\left(\sum_{a \in R} A_a M_a(t)\exp\left(-\frac{A_a\sigma_a^2}{4r_a} + \sigma_a\sqrt{\frac{A_a}{2r_a}}Z\right)\right)\right)\right),$$
where $\sigma_a$ is the volatility of asset $a$ and $Z$ is a standard
normal random variable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that if our exposure was only to one or more non-risky assets (e.g.
&lt;code&gt;USD&lt;/code&gt; if that is what profit is measured in), then we return to the
conventional definition of net assets being just the sum of all asset
exposures. That is the reason that we need to take the exponential at
the start of the expression. We also note that in all of the discussion
above, the conditions for whether trades were worth making or not are
precisely equivalent to whether the trade increases this specific
definition of $X_0$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;assumption-busting&#34;&gt;Assumption Busting&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;brownian-motion&#34;&gt;Brownian Motion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A very natural assumption to bust is the idea that the Brownian Motion
for the mid-price of an asset has constant volatility $\sigma$. Instead,
we can say that the volatility is function of time and so
$$\mathrm{d}M_t = \sigma(t) \mathrm{d}B_t,$$ where
$M$ is the mid-price and $B$ is a standard Brownian Motion (with
volatility 1). This $\sigma(t)$ can be fit in wide variety of ways. For
example, we may try to fit the volatility to periodic functions with
periods over a day (to model how volatility changes at different times
of the day) and over a week (to model how volatility changes on
different different days of the week). The volatility can also be based
on very recent low-latency observations of market-wide and
asset-specific volatility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;constants-r-and-t-t&#34;&gt;Constants $r$ and $t&amp;rsquo;-t$&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rate at which hedging trades take place clearly isn&amp;rsquo;t constant and
depend on wide variety of factors, including the periodic factors
mentioned for volatility. This can be modelled and fit based on
historical trading. Another factor that will affect rate of hedging $r$
is the amount of inventory of a certain token available. Once we start
running low on inventory, $r$ should rapidly tend towards 0.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The time between sending an order and the hedging desk hearing a
confirmation has a very large variance. However, again this can be
modelled based on historical data as a log-normal variable. Then for
every expression involving $t&amp;rsquo;-t$, we can simply take the expected value
averaging over the distribution of $t&amp;rsquo; - t$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;no-adverse-selection&#34;&gt;No adverse selection&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to model adverse selection, we have to build on top of the
model given in the equation in the &amp;ldquo;Brownian Motion&amp;rdquo; subsection,
by adding a negative drift term and an
increased variance term. Thus in a short period of time immediately
after a trade on a certain exchange $E$, takes place, the mid-price
follows the stochastic process:
$$\mathrm{d}M_t = \mu_E \mathrm{d}t + (\sigma(t) + \kappa_E)\mathrm{d}B_t,$$
where $\mu_E \leq 0$ and $\kappa_E \geq 0$ can be fitted according to
historical observations. In fact, the &amp;ldquo;short period of time&amp;rdquo; description
can also be fitted so that the $\mu_E$ and $\kappa_E$ decay
exponentially to 0 as time after the trade increases, with exponential
half-life $\tau_E$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not inclding $A_{\text{abs}}(x) \equiv 0$, where $U(x) \equiv x$
up to equivalence&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The $\pm$ sign is there to make the function increasing.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;cf. Alameda Research.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trade rate can have units of dollars per hour, for example.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The proof of this statement follows from Fubini&amp;rsquo;s Theorem. The
details are left as an exercise to the reader.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	</channel>
</rss>
